A Guide to the Legislative Petitions of the General Assembly, 1776-1865
Library of Virginia
Flour Inspection/Industry - There are 106 records in the database from citizens, farmers, millers, flour manufacturers, and others regarding flour inspection laws, the establishment of flour inspections, and the rates for flour inspection. Noteworthy are the following petitions: Peter J. Chevallie asking for the incorporation of the Gallego Milling Company for the manufacture of flour (Richmond City - 1833/12/31); Virginia State Agricultural Society asking for the repeal of all laws relating to inspection of flour quality in the Commonwealth (Buckingham Co. - 1856/01/12); and Peter J. Chevallie asking that the President & Directors of the James River Company be authorized to relieve him from the water rent which he is chargeable since the burning of his mills (Richmond City - 1836/02/15).
Free Negroes - There are 660 records in the database respecting free negroes. The petitions originate from freedmen, colonization societies, citizens, executors & administrators, slaves, Quakers, and others. A large part of these petition relate to requests by former slaves to remain in the Commonwealth. In addition, these petitions also relate to appropriations or aid to colonization societies, charters for colonization societies, the removal of free negroes from the Commonwealth, the sale of liquor to free negroes, prohibitions against free negroes from owning dogs, and restrictions on free negroes & mulattoes in the sale of produce.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: American Colonization Society asking for assistance from the state of Virginia in finding an asylum on the coast of Africa (signed by Bushrod Washington, President of the Society) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1826/12/22); Free Persons of Color asking for a law authorizing free persons of color, as well as slaves, to perform the ceremony of the burial of the dead (Richmond City - 1834/12/17); James (alias James Lafayette), former slave of William Armistead emancipated in 1786, asking for a law allowing a small sum for his service during the Revolutionary War (New Kent Co. - 1818/12/28); Religious Society of Friends asking that the law providing for the emancipation of slaves by will, and the law respecting the stealing & selling of free persons, may be revised & amended (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1802/12/17); Richmond Free Persons of Color asking for a law authorizing them to erect a place of public worship to be called the Baptist African Church (Richmond City - 1823/12/03); Society of Friends asking for the repeal of the law passed in 1806 requiring free negroes to leave the Commonwealth within one year of emancipation (Frederick Co. - 1827/12/11); and Society of Friends residing in Berkeley, Frederick, Jefferson, Fairfax, & Alexandria asking for the modification of the law prohibiting the education of free negroes (Alexandria - 1848/02/26).
Indians - There are 88 records in the database regarding Indians and Indian affairs. Included are petitions from citizens, Nottoway Indians, Pamunkey Indians, and others in relation to compensation for service against the Indians on the frontier, land purchased from Indians, security from depredations & incursions on the western frontier, and the sale of Indian lands belonging to the Nottoway Indians.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: George Rogers Clark asking that land conveyed by deed to him from the Indians may be confirmed (Kentucky Counties - 1780/05/27); George Croghan asking for confirmation of his title to lands in the west purchased from Indians (Augusta Co. - 1779/06/09); Richard Epperson & Catlit Jones, employed as soldiers to protect the inhabitants of Kentucky against the Indians, asking for relief for their wounds (certified by Daniel Boone) (Kentucky Counties - 1777/11/06); Nathaniel Gist asking that the treaty with the Cherokee Indians be confirmed, and that an island in the Holstein River that was granted him by the Cherokee Indians in 1761 or 1762 also be confirmed (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1777/11/19); Inhabitants of Northampton County asking for an act to appoint trustees to lay off a convenient part of the land appropriated for the use of the Gingaskin Tribe and to lease out the remainder annually (1784/11/26); Inhabitants of Northampton County asking that the land appropriated for the Gingaskin Tribe may be sold and the money arising from the sale appropriated for the maintenance of the Indians (1787/10/10); George Jackson asking that the House adopt measures to assert the rights of the Commonwealth against the Indiana Company (includes copy of deed with the Six Nations in 1744) (Harrison Co. - 1804/12/04); John Gabriel Jones & George Rogers Clark asking for forces for their protection from the Indians west of the Ohio River (Kentucky Counties - 1776/10/19); Nottoway Indians asking for an act for the sale of some of their lands and the money arising from the sale out into the hands of trustees for the support of petitioners (Southampton Co. - 1792/10/09 & 1803/12/09); Pamunkey Indians asking for a law vesting in the trustees of the tribe the power to lease out their land (King William Co. - 1812/12/04); Proprietors of the land on the Ohio called Indiana asking that no act pass impeaching or prejudicing their titles to lands paid for by treaty with Indians and in recompense for depredations committed by them (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1777/06/03); and Trustees of the Gingaskin Tribe asking for the repeal of the law of 1792 to authorize commissioners to divide the land among the members of the tribe, and to lay off roads through the land (Northampton Co. - 1812/12/02).
Land/Real Estate - There are 2,306 records in the database related to land or real estate. Included are petitions from citizens, administrators, churchwardens, ministers, heirs, vestries, mayors, aldermen, overseers of the poor, fraternal organizations, trustees of academies, colleges, towns, churches, executors, soldiers, and officers. These petitions concern assessments, land titles, surveys, courthouses, extension of the corporate limits of towns, bounty lands for war service, glebe lands, escheats, administrations of estates, delinquent lands, improvements of lots, waste & unappropriated lands, county boundaries, property destroyed by the British during the Revolutionary War, and sequestered property.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Samuel G. Adams asking that the grant for a reservoir on the Public Square may be confirmed to him for the use of the surplus water in the two springs on the Square (Richmond City - 1808/12/22); American citizens in Paris asking for aliens to hold real property in the United States (Miscellaneous (chronological) - 1845/01/04); Samuel & James Barron, heirs of James Barron, Commodore of the State Navy, asking for compensation for the bounty lands & commutation of pay due to them as heirs (Elizabeth City Co. - 1795/11/25); Directors of Public Buildings asking for the appointment of a committee of the General Assembly to aide them in relocating the Capitol & other state buildings in Richmond (Richmond City - 1779/11/08); Daniel Boone asking for an act directing the Register to issue him a Land Office Treasury warrant for 628 acres of land purchased by him on 21 February 1783 (Kentucky Counties - 1794/11/24); Citizens of Richmond asking that land on Capitol Square may be loaned to James Warrell for the purpose of erecting a museum of natural & artificial curiosities (1815/12/18); George Rogers Clark asking that the land conveyed by deed to him from the Indians may be confirmed (Kentucky Counties - 1780/05/27); Jubal Early, guardian of the heirs of Abner Early, asking for a law to authorize the sale of three small pieces of mountain land (Montgomery Co. - 1841/12/30); Governor Joseph Johnston to the Speaker of the House of Delegates submitting a letter from Jefferson Davis, Secretary of War, requesting that the government be authorized to purchase the necessary land to construct the Washington Aqueduct (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1854/01/21); Richard Lorton, co-partner of James Warrell for the purpose of erecting a building on the Public Square for a museum, asking for an act relinquishing the right of the Commonwealth to the property & alterations to enable to lease the property (Richmond City - 1835/12/31); Mayor, Aldermen, & Commonalty of Richmond asking for an act declaring that all real property lying between the James River and the eastern & northern boundary of the city of Richmond be deemed a part of the city (1791/11/01); Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, & Common Council of Williamsburg asking for an appropriation for rebuilding the former Capitol, or granting the lot on which it stood in the city of Williamsburg (1832/12/10); Merchants, Masters of Vessels, & Mariners asking for an act ceding to the United States as many acres of land on Point Comfort necessary for the establishment of a lighthouse (Elizabeth City Co. - 1797/12/20); Edward Mitchell asking for permission to build a lighthouse (Norfolk City - 1785/12/10); Officers of the State of Pennsylvania asking that the Register may be directed to grant them land in Virginia as veterans of Braddock's War by virtue of a proclamation of the King of Great Britain in 1763 (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1790/11/27); Samuel Overton asking for additional compensation for his land condemned by a writ of ad quod damnum for the use of the public in the establishment of a Manufactory of Arms (Richmond City - 1798/12/05); Proprietors of the Armory Iron Works asking for an extension to their lease from the Commonwealth of the ground adjoining the Armory (Richmond City - 1864/01/07); Executors of John A. Washington asking for the appointment of commissioners for dividing their proportion of one-twelfth of the property (Westmoreland Co. - 1787/11/22); and Charles L. Wingfield asking for a law authorizing the Treasurer to pay him the value of a certain lot which was condemned for the use of the Penitentiary in Richmond (Norfolk Borough - 1837/01/23).
Manufacturers/Manufacturing Companies - There are 215 records in the database concerning manufacturers & manufacturing companies. The petitions within this category originate from citizens, manufacturers, mill owners, manufacturing companies, mechanics, and others. The petitions mainly relate to the incorporation of manufacturing companies for the production of iron, cotton, wool, hemps, arms, flour, cloth, silk, salt, paper, flax, and other items. In addition, the petitions concern the construction of milldams and railroads.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Peter J. Chevallie asking for the incorporation f the Gallego Manufacturing Company (Richmond City - 1833/12/05 & 31); Inhabitants of Kentucky asking for the erection of salt works on property now owned by individuals (signed by Daniel Boone) (1777/11/25); Proprietors of the Armory Iron works asking for an extension of their lease from the Commonwealth of the grounds adjoining the Armory (Richmond City - 1864/01/07); R. Archer & Company asking for an extension of the lease of the Armory Building for ten years (Richmond City - 1852/11/27); George Wheeler asking for compensation for erecting works for the manufacture of arms (Culpeper Co. - 1804/12/19); and Harpers Ferry & Shenandoah Manufacturing Company's plan & report with a descriptive view of the Island of Virginius at Harpers Ferry connected with their application for a charter (Jefferson Co. - 1845/01/13).
Militia/Public Guard - There are 669 records in the database regarding the militia & Public Guard. Included are petitions from militia units, soldiers, officers, administrators, members of the Public guard, widows, citizens, religious groups, fire companies, sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, and others. The petitions regard changes to militia units & organization, requests for arms, relief from fines for nonattendance at musters, compensation for services, pensions, militia laws, exemptions from militia duty, claims for provisions, regimental courts of inquiry, the restoration of brigade inspectors, changes to the locations of officer's training & musters, the formation of new regimental districts, and the incorporation of militia units.
Noteworthy are the following: Blair Bolling, Commandant of the Public Guard, asking for compensation for his services as Superintendent of Public Buildings (Richmond City - 1831/02/18); Citizens of Lynchburg asking for a general law for the immediate organization of all capable men within each magisterial district of the state between the ages of 50 & 60 years and all resident exempts from Confederate service between the ages of 17 & 50 into companies (1860/02/17); Citizens of Petersburg asking that a guard be stationed in the town to protect against insurrection (N.D. - ca. 1802); Citizens of Rockingham County asking for a modification in the establishment of the Public Guard in Richmond and at the Lexington Arsenal (1831/02/17); Charles Dimmock asking that the duties of the Captain of the Public Guard & Superintendent of the Armory be separated from the Superintendent of Public Buildings (Richmond City - 1856/01/12); Norfolk Light Infantry Blues asking for an appropriation to enlarge & improve their Gun House (Norfolk City - 1851/02/10); James Paxton asking for compensation for additional duties given him as Captain of the Public Guard at the Lexington Arsenal (Rockbridge Co. - 1826/12/07); Judgment of the Circuit Superior Court of Law & Chancery for Henrico & Richmond regarding the case of Charles Dimmock, Captain of the Public Guard, against the Commonwealth (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1846/12/30).
Mining/Mining Companies - There are 158 records in the database from citizens, colliers, landowners, coal companies, gold mining companies, miners, and others regarding the incorporation of mining companies, the construction of canals & railroads for the transportation of coal, reassessment of lands, and tolls. Noteworthy are the following petitions: Benjamin Coleman asking for the incorporation of the Richmond Mining Company (Stafford Co. - 1834/02/05) and James Parberry asking that the lands adjacent to the mines be reserved as fuel for mines (written by Patrick Henry) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1782/05/25).
Miscellaneous - There are 815 records in the database of a more general nature from citizens, committees, overseers of the poor, and others. These petitions relate to a wide variety of topics including receipts & withdrawals of unidentified petitions, the anti-dueling law, appointments as doorkeeper to the House of Delegates, usury, the act of retrocession, days of thanksgiving, the removal of Richmond as the seat of government, the eastern Lunatic Asylum, the trapping of water fowl, the cutting of woods for fuel, lumber inspection, pay of delegates, the alien & sedition laws, debts, the District of Kentucky, the conduct of delegates, the treaty of peace with Great Britain, the solemnization of marriages, poor houses, milldams, lotteries, and printers.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Thomas Ash asking for authority to recover by Diving Bells, or otherwise, the guns and other property of an English Frigate which was sunk in the York RIver during the Revolutionary War (Gloucester Co. - 1852/02/10); George Catlin, artist of the Virginia Convention, offering his painting to the state of Virginia (Richmond City - 1831/03/25); Committee of the Historical Society of Virginia asking for the erection of a monument to George Washington in Richmond (Richmond City - 1849/02/05); Freeholders of Washington County asking for a review of the boundary line between Virginia & North Carolina which was extended by commissioners on 1779 & readjusted in 1802 (includes affidavit from Capt. Meriwether Lewis) (1810/12/20); articles of agreement between Gov. Wilson C. Nicholas and Richard Harris to erect the Public arsenal in Lexington (Richmond City - 1808/01/14); and Charles D. Yale asking that the Capitol be heated with Dr. James Bolton's improves warm air furnaces (Richmond City - 1854/01/28 & 1855/12/05).
Name Changes - There are 52 records in the database documenting citizens' requests for name changes. These petitions also relate to applications to change the names of towns or companies. Noteworthy are the following: citizens of Evansham asking for the incorporation of the town to be called Wytheville (Wythe Co. - 1839/01/14); the Mercantile Library Association asking for a change in their name to the Richmond Library Association (Richmond City - 1841/01/20); and Trustees of Washington Academy asking for a change in their name to Washington College (Rockbridge Co. - 1812/12/11).
Navigation/Navigation Companies - There are 1,134 records in the database concerning navigation & navigation companies. Included are petitions from citizens, canal companies, navigation companies, pilots, ship owners, merchants, mill owners, stockholders, trustees, and others. The petitions relate to the construction of wharves, the erection of milldams, declarations that waterways be declared public highways, steamboats, extensions of improvements of navigation, incorporations of canal, navigation, & steamboat companies, amendments & modifications to the charters of canal & navigations companies, pilots & rates of pilotage, capital stock of navigation companies, and the removal of obstructions to the navigation of waterways.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Citizens of Richmond, Manchester, & other parts of Virginia asking for a law incorporating a company in Richmond for the purpose of trading to ports & places eastward of the Cape of Good Hope & elsewhere under the title of the "Richmond East India Company" (Richmond City - 1817/12/30); Alexander Martin & Thomas Binbury, speaker of the General Assembly of North Carolina, asking for keeping open the navigation of Ocracoke Inlet by fitting out some armed vessels at the port of South Quay to cooperate with their ships (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1781/11/22); M. F. Maury asking for a charter incorporating a company to establish a line of steamers from New York to ports of Brazil to be called the Amazonia Steamship Company (Norfolk Borough - 1852/01/28); Merchants, Masters of Vessels, & Mariners asking for an act ceding to the United States as many acres of land on Point Comfort necessary for the establishment of a lighthouse (Elizabeth City Co. - 1797/12/20); President & Directors of the Potomac Company asking that the acts may pass by the Assemblies of Maryland & Virginia for a canal at each or either of the Great Falls (signed by George Washington) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1785/12/09); President & Directors of the Potomac Company asking that the acts of the Assemblies of Maryland & Virginia may be passed whereby the company may be indulged with time until 17 November 1790 for making & improving the navigation between the Great Falls & Fort Cumberland (signed by George Washington) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1786/11/09); Rumseian Society asking for an act granting James Rumsey exclusive privilege of making & lending his inventions including his steamboat (Berkeley Co. - 1788/11/15); James Rumsey asking for an act granting him the sole right of constructing, navigating, & employing boats constructed upon a newly invented model (Berkeley Co. - 1784/11/08); Inhabitants of Albemarle, Louisa, & Fluvanna asking for the incorporation of a company to open navigation on the Rivanna River and authority to receive tolls (signed by Thomas Jefferson) (Albemarle Co. - 1810/12/13).
Organizations - There are 398 records in the database from fraternal organizations, agricultural societies, insurance companies, colonization societies, fire companies, library associations & companies, temperance societies, literary societies, mechanic societies, medical societies, merchants, and other citizens. These petitions primarily concern requests for charters or acts of incorporation, but also lotteries, appropriations, and exemptions from militia or jury duty.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: American Colonization Society asking for assistance from the state of Virginia in finding an asylum on the coast of Africa (signed by Bushrod Washington, President of the Society) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1826/12/22); Martin Becker & others asking for an act of incorporation of the Great Council of the Improved Order of Red Men of the State of Virginia (Ohio Co. - 1842/02/23); Central Southern Rights Association asking for the charter of a company with the right to construct two steamers for the purpose of carrying passengers & freight from a point on the James River to Norfolk and across the Atlantic Ocean to Liverpool or other foreign ports (Norfolk Borough - 1851/12/13); Colonization Society of Virginia asking for aid from the General Assembly (signed by John Marshall) (Richmond City - 1831/12/20); William Foushee & others asking for a law to incorporate the Medical Society of Virginia (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1823/12/08); Hollywood Cemetery Company asking for an act of incorporation (Richmond City - 1849/12/27); and the Jefferson & Washington Societies of the University of Virginia asking for an act of incorporation (Albemarle Co. - 1840/02/08).
Paper Money - There are 109 records in the database from citizens, banks, merchants, and others respecting banks' requests to issue notes in denominations less than five dollars, relief from the depreciation of paper money during the Revolutionary War, tender laws, and taxes.
Pardons/Releases from Fines, Judgments, etc. - There are 995 records in the database documenting applications for pardons, commutations of sentences, and releases from fines, judgments, & recognizances. There are petitions from citizens, sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, securities, executors, administrators, clerks, soldiers, and others. The petitions relate to fines for unlawful gambling, retailing goods or ardent spirits without a license, non-attendance of militia or jury duty, failure of sheriffs or deputy sheriffs to make tax payments on time, assault & battery, violation of the anti-dueling law, counterfeiting, commutation of punishments or remission of remaining sentences, receipt of stolen goods, forgery, arson, robbery, high treason, forfeited recognizances, horse stealing, murder, and nonpayment of taxes.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Citizens of Albemarle County who served as jurors in the case of John S. Mosby, a student in the University, convicted of unlawful shooting of George Turpin, asking that he be pardoned & have a fine remitted (1854/01/14); Jacob A. Levy & Jacob Ezekiel asking for the remission of a fine imposed on them as Jews for violating the Sabbath (Richmond City - 1846/01/28 & 1848/03/08); Mann Page, executor of John Tayloe, deceased, asking for a pardon for Tayloe's slave Billy who was sentenced to death for treason & reprieved by Governor Thomas Jefferson (Prince William Co. - 1781/06/07); and John Clarke protesting against charges against him as Superintendent of the Manufactory of Arms (Richmond City - 1809/02/13).